<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Seven wise masters of Rome]</title>
            <title>Seven sages of Rome. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1493</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11029</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114568</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849793</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849793</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14961</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11029)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14961)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1558:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Seven wise masters of Rome]</title>
                  <title>Seven sages of Rome. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2+] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Richard Pynson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1493]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title and imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Adapted in verse by John Rolland in: The seuen seages translatit out of prois in Scottis meter (STC 21254).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; consists of 2 leaves only.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Trinity College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14961:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:14961:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> the mete was redy: and the tyme of the day was come to go to dyner / the fader cam w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a baſyn and an ewyr. and the moder with a towel ſaynge ſyr. Syr alle thynge is redy / pleaſe it you to waſſhe: and whan the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſawe that: he ſmyled and ſaid to him ſelf Nowe is the ſong of the nyghtyngale true. for my fader and my moder ſhulde gladely fulfille as I ſayde: if I my ſelfe wold ther / to conſente and ſuffre theym. But he wolde nat ſuffre theym to doo him that ſeruyce: ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge / youre age is to be honoured: and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I wol nat of it. and called vnto hym one of his ſeruauntes the whych ſerued him therof. Than ſayde the knyght / ye wol nat ſuffre vs to do it to oure honoure: for we are nat worthy therto. The kynge ſayd. Haue nat I ſaide that for the honoure of youre a / ge I forbere it: whan the kynge was ſet at the table. he ſet his moder on the right hand of him / and his fader on his lefte ſyde. and they aſmoche as they myght behelde his vp ſage and countenaunce. The dyner ended</p>
            <p>¶the kynge entred in to a chambre / and
<pb facs="tcp:14961:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->made the knyght with his lady to coome in to him: and commaunded al other to a voi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and go oute / and whan they were thus a / lone: the kynge ſaide vnto theym. haue ye no children. They anſweryd we haue ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſonne ne doughter. And the kynge ſaid had ye neuer none. The knyght anſwered we haue had one ſonne: but he is long a go dede. The kynge aſked of what dethe dyed he. The knyght ſayd: a natural deth. Tho ſayde the kinge. if I may otherwiſe knowe that he dyed. than are ye founde wyth a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faute. Tho aſked the knight. My lorde wherfore inquere ye thus after oure ſonne? The kynge anſwered. that do I nat withe oute cauſe / and therfore I wolle knowe of what dethe he dyed: and if ye wolle nat tell me I ſhal cauſe you to dye a ſhameful deth whan they herde that they fil to ground vp on ther knees afore him and aſkid him mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy and foryeuenes of theyr lyues. The kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge wold nat ſuffre them to knele / but ſhort<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly tooke theym and ſayde. To that intente cam I nat to youre houſe to ete your brede
<pb facs="tcp:14961:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->and to betraye you / but ſay me the trouthe &amp; ye ſhalbe ſaued. for it is yeuen me to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande that ye haue put him to deth. &amp; if that come in iugement ye muſte dye a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meful dethe. Than ſaide the knyght. forde pardone me of my lyfe &amp; I ſhalle ſhewe you the verraye trouthe. The kynge ſayde: fere nat / for I ſhal do you no harme. Tho ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de he. Soueraygne lorde we hadde a ſonne only that was wyſe and lettryd and ryghte well vnderſtande. And vpon a tyme as he ſtode afore vs &amp; ſerued at the table. There cam a nyghtingale that right ſwetly ſange whoos ſonge he began to interprete &amp; telle vs what it ment / and ſayde. This bird ſyn / geth that I ſhal be come ſo grete and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a lorde that it ſhalbe to youre honoure &amp; aduaunſement in ſuche wyſe: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye my fader ſhalbe glad to holde the baſyn withe water to waſſhe in myn handes. and my moder ye towel if I wolle ſuffre it. And whan I herd that: I was fore meuyd and toke and caſte him into the ſee for to drowne. Tho ſayde the kynge: what euyl might haue come to
<pb facs="tcp:14961:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->you / if he had been made ſo greate &amp; mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty / me thynketh it ſhulde haue ben your ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noure and proufyt. The knyght ſaide lord it was no reſon but a woodneſſe. The kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge anſwered: that was a grete foliſſhnes of you that ye wolde doo ayenſte the ordenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and wyl of god. But now ye ſhal knowe for trouth that I am youre ſon that ye caſt into the ſee / and god of hys greate mercy &amp; goodneſſe hathe ſauyd me: and by his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce hath brought me to this ſtate and digny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te. And the fader and moder herynge that withe fere and ioye replenyſſhed fyll flat to the grounde: whom he frendly and louyng / ly toke vp / ſaynge feare nat: butt rather be glad and ioyous / for ye ſhal no thyng ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre / but my evaltacion ſhalbe youre glorye and ioye and proufyte for euyr / and kyſte bothe his fader and moder wythe greate ioy and gladneſſe. Tho began the moder to we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe. Than ſaide the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wepe nat / but be of goode conforte and chere. for in my realme ſhal ye be taken and honoured abooue me durynge my lyfe: in al thynges. and tooke</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14961:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
